Nicole: An Incident post-mortem takes
place after the event to help teams
better prepare for future incidents.
Abraham: These are also known as
‘post incident reviews’ or ‘root cause
analysis’ and doing this can help create
a culture of continuous improvement.
Nicole: It shouldn’t specifically
apportion blame but should be
about understanding why and how
the incident took place and how
future attacks can be prevented.
All parties should be able to
speak more freely when blame
is taken out of the equation.
Abraham: At the time of the attack
the first response is to restore
service and mitigate the incident.
But the post-mortem gives chance
to take the whole incident
apart and see what went wrong.
The person in charge is the incident
post-mortem coordinator and will
be chosen by the person in charge
of responding to the incident.
Nicole: The coordinator will then
involve and liaise with the other
members of the appropriate teams who were
involved in responding to the incident.
Once they have accumulated the
relevant information, they’ll organise
a discussion and assemble a report.
A post-mortem is usually a collaborative
process orchestrated by the coordinator.
Abraham: Most organisations will
develop their own post-mortem
process, structure and documentation
according to their needs.
But on the whole, they
often follow the same steps:
Nicole: The meeting- this will
involve all those who were
involved in the incident response.
Any documentation such as
incident logs should be presented.
There may also be more individual meetings
to gain more details with those involved
in mitigating the incident directly.
It should also be made clear to all team
members, that the incident was blameless!
Abraham: The Post-mortem Report-this
presents all the information and
conclusions gained from the meeting
and a record of the event that
can be referred to in the future.
It should include incident details,
root cause analysis, the incident
timeline, any actions, and any
conclusions and steps to be taken.
Nicole: Dissemination of the
report and findings- this should
be distributed to all involved and
to management and decision makers.
It may also need to be made public
to reassure customers and clients.
Abraham: Follow up actions-
If recommendations are made
these should be acted on.
An incident post-mortem should be a valid
process and not just a tick box exercise.
It should be clearly detailed enough to
draw conclusions as to what works and
what doesn’t and how this can be remedied.
Nicole: Remember incidents are
a learning opportunity, a chance
to uncover vulnerabilities
and mitigate future incidents.